Finding Aid for Carl E. Gehring papers, 1926-1965
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carl E. Gehring papers 1926-1965
Gehring, Carl Ernest, 1897-1966.
10 microfilms
4 oversize volumes
2 linear feet
851279 Aa 2; AC
Music critic for the Ann Arbor News and musical composer. Manuscripts of musical compositions, scrapbooks with newspaper clippings of his criticisms, and sound recordings of performances of his compositions, and microfilm of his compositions.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Frederick W. Gehring (donor no. 4840 ).
The collection is open to research.
Carl Gehring was born May 3, 1897, in Cleveland, Ohio. He was a graduate of the University of Michigan School of Music in 1921, and in 1923, he received an A.B. degree from the University's College of Literature, Science and the Arts. Thereafter, he studied musical composition with Thorvald Otterstrom of Chicago.
Throughout his career, Gehring was first a newspaperman and then a composer. He went to work for the Ann Arbor Times News in 1925 as that newspaper's telegraph editor. In 1926, he became the music reviewer of the News, serving in this capacity from 1926 to 1934 and then again from 1943 to 1961. In addition to being music reviewer, Gehring also served as the News' State Editor from 1941 until his retirement in 1962.
As a composer, Gehring wrote the score for about sixty songs, numerous piano solos, miniatures for piano, two band marches, an orchestral suite, and a cantata for contralto, male chorus and orchestra. Many of Gehring's works are based upon the writings of American writers, notably Robert Frost, Emily Dickinson, and Robinson Jeffers.
Gehring also wrote articles on musical subjects for various journals and newspapers. He was a member of the Michigan Composer's Club, and was a participant in a number of the Club's concerts and competitions. Gehring died in September 1966.
The Gehring collection consists of manuscripts of musical compositions, scrapbooks with newspaper clippings of his criticisms, and sound recordings of performances of his compositions, and microfilm of his compositions. The collection is organized into four series: Correspondence, essays and other materials; Scrapbooks; Musical Compositions; and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor news.; Gehring, Carl Ernest, 1897-1966.; Music--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Musicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor news.; Baseball.; Gehring, Carl Ernest, 1897-1966.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Piano music.; Piano music (Pianos (2); Songs (High voice) with piano.; Studio showcase (Radio program)
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Krimm, Marilyn.; Austin, Carolyn.; Jacobson, Elaine.; WUOM (Radio station: Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence, essays and other materials
  - Biographical materials (Box 1)
    (include photographs)
  - Correspondence October 16-17, 1947 concerning Grand Rapids Concert (Box 1)
  - "Opinions of Correspondents on Music Reviews "
    - Undated 1926-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1929-1934 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1951 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Essays, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Ind-X Magazine: music reviews (Box 1)
  - Michigan Composers' Club materials 1943-1947 (Box 1)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series consists of copies of his reviews and programs for performances of his work.
  - Scrapbooks of music reviews, 3 volumes (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook: Music reviews written for Ann Arbor Daily News, June 1926-June 1934, 1941-1943 and reviews written for Ann Arbor Ind-X, October 1935-May 1937 (Volume 1)
  - Scrapbook: Music reviews written for Ann Arbor News, November 1943-June 1954 (Volume 2)
  - Scrapbook: Music reviews written for Ann Arbor News, October 1954-May 1961 and programs of performances (Volume 3)
- Musical Compositions
  Gehring's musical compositions includes both manuscript and published versions of his work. The series is made up of original and microfilm copies of his work.
  - Inventory to Carl Gehring compositions (Box 3)
  - Manuscript sheet music
    - Unnumbered, and Opus 2, #3; Opus 4, #1-5; Opus 5, #2 (Box 3)
    - Opus 8, #1-2; Opus 11, #1, 4 (Box 3)
    - Opus 12, "Lament: Shine, Perishing Republic" (Volume 4)
    - Opus 13, #1-2; Opus 15, #1-3, 5 (Box 3)
    - Opus 18 (Box 3)
    - Opus 19, #1-2, 4-5; Opus 20, #1-3 (Box 3)
    - Opus 21, #1-4; Opus 22, 1-7. (Box 3)
    - Opus 23, #2-3; Opus 24, #1-2; Opus 25, #1, 3 (Box 3)
    - Opus 26, #1-3; Opus 27, #1-4 (Box 3)
    - Opus 28, movements 1-2 (Box 3)
    - Opus 28, movements 4, 6-7 (Box 3)
    - Opus 29, #1-2 (Box 3)
  - Published sheet music (Box 3)
  - Titled compositions, microfilm negatives
    - Bereft (Reel 1)
    - Once by the Pacific (Reel 1)
    - Take Hands (Reel 2)
    - Revelation (Reel 2)
    - Capriccio (Reel 3)
    - Dance Fantasy (Reel 3)
    - Idyl (Reel 3)
    - Finale (Reel 3)
    - Song Without Words (Reel 3)
    - Valse Gracieuse (Reel 3)
    - Tree at My Window (Reel 4)
    - I'm Nobody! Who Are You? (Reel 4)
    - Unsung (Reel 4)
    - One star (Reel 4)
    - I Like a Look of Agony (Reel 5)
    - It Tossed and Tossed (Reel 5)
    - I Years Had Been From Home (Reel 5)
    - The Spider As An Artist (Reel 5)
    - When Roses Cease to Bloom, Dear (Reel 5)
    - The Rose Did Caper on Her Cheek (Reel 5)
    - Heart Not So Heavy as Mine (Reel 5)
    - Tavern (Reel 6)
    - Sea Fog (Reel 6)
    - Proteus (Reel 6)
    - Little Flowers of Love and Wonder (Reel 6)
    - Prelude in G Minor (Reel 7)
    - Prelude in D Minor (Reel 7)
    - Intermezzo in B-flat (Reel 7)
    - Intermezzo (Elegy) in F Minor (Reel 7)
    - Intermezzo in D-flat Major (Reel 7)
    - Intermezzo in C (Reel 7)
    - Waltz in A Major (Reel 7)
    - Waltz in C Minor (Reel 7)
    - Intermezzo in G Major (Reel 7)
    - Valse Miniature (Reel 8)
    - Legend: A Nursery Tale (Reel 8)
    - The Pasture (Reel 9)
    - The Birthplace (Reel 9)
    - Acquainted with the Night (Reel 9)
    - Flower-gathering (Reel 9)
    - A Peck of Gold (Reel 9)
    - Acceptance (Reel 9)
    - Hill Wife Cycle
      - Loneliness (Reel 9)
      - House Fear (Reel 9)
      - The Smile (Reel 9)
      - The Oft-repeated Dream (Reel 9)
      - The Impulse (Reel 9)
    - If I Can Stop One Heart from Breaking (Reel 10)
    - Because I Could Not Stop for Death (Reel 10)
    - Autumn Sorrow (Reel 10)
- Sound recordings
  The Sound Recordings series consist of reel-to-reel tapes of performances of some of Gehring's work.
  - A Program of Robert Frost, Songs / music by Carl Gehring--WNYC-New York City April 6, 1960, 1); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
  - Ten Songs by Carl Gehring / Marilyn Krimm, soprano: Elaine Jacobson, accompanist. October 2, 1961, 2); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (titles include: October; Autumn Crocus; Late on a Cool and Lonely Day; November Pain; Autumn Sorrow; In a Grave-Yard; Oriflamme; Little Son; Harlem Shadows; The Lynching)
  - The Readers' Almanac: Songs by Carl Gehring, based on Poems by American Negro Authors.--WNYC-New York City May 5, 1962, 3); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
  - Rameau/Gehring/Bach: Two-Piano program broadcast March 21, 1963, 4); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents, Gehring songs: The Lily Pond; Ginger Snap; Tom and Jerry; Hither and Yon; Alphonse and Gaston; Tick Tock; Spic and Span; Jack and Jill; Nip and Tuck; Moonlight on a Pool)
  - Piano Pieces in a Program of American Music / Barbara Holmquist, pianist December 31, 1963, 5); 5" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: G. Mason, Silhouette in A; E. MacDowell, Will O' the Wisp In Autumn; D. G. Mason, Whippoorwill Chimney Swallows; Carl Gehring, Intermezzo Prelude in D minor)
  - Studio Showcase: Gehring, Sonqs / Reah Sadowsky, Pianist,--WUOM-Ann Arbor, Mich. April 28, 1964, 6); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: Prelude in G Minor; Cavatina (Sadness); Lullaby; Intermezzo in G-Major; Suite for Piano Solo in Four Movements)
  - Studio Showcase: Gehring Songs Based on Poems by Emily Dickinson / Marilyn Krimm, soprano; Elaine Jacobson, Pianist May 28, 1964, 7); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: If I Can Stop One Heart From Breaking; Because I Could Not Stop for Death; I'm Nobody! Who Are You?; I Like a Look of Agony; It Tossed and Tossed; When Roses Cease to Bloom, Dear; 1 Years Had Been From Home; The Rose Did Caper on Her Cheek; Heart Not So Heavy as Mine; The Snider as an Artist)
  - Studio Showcase: Gehring Songs Based on Poems by Emily Dickinson (revised for broadcast) May 28, 1964, 8); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
  - The Readers' Almanac [broadcast]: Emily Dickinson Songs. Music by Carl Gehring (contents unknown)--WNYC-New York City October 26, 1964, 9); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
  - WUOM Studio Showcase / Frances Felbeck. Pianist, November 3 ? 1964, 10); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: Intermezzo in D-Flat Major; Intermezzo in F-Minor (Elegy); Waltz in A-Major; Miniature Waltz; Prelude in D-Minor; Waltz in C-Minor; Intermezzo in C)
  - WUOM Studio Showcase: Ten Songs by Carl Gehring / Soprano, Carolyn Austin; accompanist, E. Jacobson circa 1965, 11); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: Morning Shadows; The Little Path; Winter Fastness; Nothing Gold Can Stay; Once by the Pacific; Bereft; One Star; Unsung; For a Moment the Wind Died)
  - Eight Songs Based on Poems by Robert Frost / Carolyn Austin;: E. Jacobson undated, 12); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (contents unknown)
  - The Readers' Almanac: Songs by Edna St. Vincent Millay, Music by Carl Gehring.---WNYC-New York City February 23, 1964, 13); 7" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
  - WUOM Studio Showcase: Suite for Piano Solo Music by Carl Gehring) / pianist, Lydia Court undated, 14) (Box 2)
    (Contents: Capriccio; Dance Fantasy; Idyl; Finale)
  - (Gehring Songs) / Carolyn Austin; E. Jacobson undated, 15) (Box 2)
    (Contents: Sea Fog; A Peck of Gold)
  - [Gehring Songs Based on Poems by Edna St. Vincent Millay] / Mary Matfeld Burdette, contralto; E. Jacobson, accompanist undated, 16); 10" reel; 7 1/2 ips (Box 2)
    (Contents: Dirge; Tavern; The Betrothal; I See So Clearly; Scrub; Elaine)